{"tossups": [{"question": "Though he did not coin the term, this physicist proposed the concept of isospin from the similarities between protons and neutrons. He\u2019s not Wheeler, but this physicist developed S-matrix theory to describe a system undergoing scattering. He published his matrix formulation of quantum mechanics in a series of papers with (*) Max Born and Pascual Jordan. A statement named for this man can be stated as h-bar over two is less than or equal to the product of the standard deviations of two conjugate variables, position and momentum. For 10 points, name this German physicist who developed the uncertainty principle.", "answer": "Werner Heisenberg", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The active stratovolcano Volc\u00e1n Bar\u00fa represents the highest point in this country. This nation controls the San Blas Islands and the damming of the Chagres River in this country created its Gatun Lake. The Miraflores is used by one prominent piece of infrastructure in this country which shares La Amistad International Park with its northern neighbor (*) Costa Rica. The most famous waterway in this nation was ceded by the US in 1999 and prevents ships from having to sail through the Straits of Magellan. For ten points, name this Central American isthmus nation which contains a namesake canal.", "answer": "Panama", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "Deities of this entity include the Aztec Chalchiuhtlicue, and the Hawaiian Namaka. One god of this place turned the woman Caenis into the warrior Caeneus after he raped her. The Japanese deity of this entity commonly takes the form of a dragon called Ryujin, and the Norse god of this place fathered a two children with his own sister. Those children, (*) Freyr and Freya, were fathered by Njord. For ten points, name this place, deities of which include the Greek Poseidon and the Roman Neptune, which refers to the part of Earth that is not land.", "answer": "the sea (accept ocean or water or any obvious equivalents)", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This empire lost the battle the Battle of Akroinon and was opposed by the H\u0101shim\u012byah sect.  Founded by Muawiyah I after victory in the First Fitna, this dynasty administered its vast holdings through six administrative diwan. This empire was overthrown after the Battle of the Zab but persisted in Al-Andalus as the Caliphate of (*) C\u00f3rdoba. Forces of this dynasty killed Husayn ibn Ali at the Battle of Karbala and were defeated by Charles Martel at Tours. For ten points, name this second Islamic caliphate based at Damascus and succeeded by the Abbasids.", "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The title poem in a collection by this author is about a man who is exiled until war breaks out, when he returns to fight. That poem is called \u201cTimoleon.\u201d A novel written by this man describes life on the island of Nuku Hiva, and is titled (*) Typee. A short story by this man includes a character who works very hard, but then refuses to do so again, repeatedly saying \u201cI would prefer not to.\u201d That story appears in this author\u2019s collection The Piazza Tales. For ten points, name this author of works such as \u201cBartleby the Scrivener,\u201d Billy Budd, and a story about a great white whale titled Moby Dick.", "answer": "Herman Melville", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In the first episode of this series, William Gant is killed for testifying in a murder trial. Frank Sobotka struggles to preserve his IBS local in this show, and is eventually stabbed to death on orders of The Greek. In this series, Marlo Stanfield comes to control the heroin trade after the decline of the (*) Barksdale organization. Stickup-man Omar Little kills Stringer Bell in this show\u2019s third season, while Kima Greggs, Cedric Daniels, and Jimmy McNulty are among the law enforcement figures featured in this series. For ten points, name this HBO crime drama set in Baltimore.", "answer": "The Wire", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "Sergei Eisenstein\u2019s Battleship Potemkin inspired two Francis Bacon depictions of this event, including his Three Studies for Figures at the Base of this event. Marc Chagall added a swastika and the words \"Ich bin jude\" to his \u201cWhite\" version of this event which shows the central figure wearing a (*) Jewish prayer shawl. The net of a hypercube replaces the central object in a Salvador Dali painting of this scene. For 10 points, name this event whose depictions are usually accompanied by the acronym \"INRI\" and show the death of Jesus Christ.", "answer": "the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Gap-junction proteins called connexin 26 and 30 are expressed in this structure and are important to its functionality. The central axis of this structure is called the modiolus, and the motor protein prestin affects OHCs in it. Presbycusis and M\u00e9ni\u00e8re's disease affect this structure, which is separated by (*) Reissner's membrane into the scala media and the scala vestibuli, which contain the endolymph and perilymph. Semicircular canals and the vestibule form the bony labyrinth along with this structure, which is not coiled in monotremes. For 10 points, name this spiral-shaped auditory structure named for its resemblance to a snail shell and namesake of a common ear implant.", "answer": "cochlea (prompt on \u201cear\u201d or \u201cinner ear\u201d)", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This position grew under Thomas Reed, who eliminated the disappearing quorum. When Democrat Jim Traficant supported Dennis Hastert for this position, he was stripped of his seniority. Frederick Muhlenberg was the first man to hold this office, and a 1910 revolt against Joseph (*) Cannon considerably limited its scope. The longest tenured holder of this office is Sam Rayburn, and James Polk is the only president to hold this position. In 1994, Newt Gingrich used the Contract with America to win this office. For ten points, name this legislative position held by Nancy Pelosi, John Boehner, and currently, Paul Ryan.", "answer": "Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One of these characters remarks that \u201closs of virtue in a female is irretrievable,\u201d one of her many vain musings. One of these characters remarks \u201cWhat are men to mountains and rocks?\u201d after learning about a proposed vacation to the Lake District. At a dinner scene in (*) Netherfield Hall, one of these characters is told to \u201cgive the other girls a chance\u201d after ostentatiously playing the piano-forte. One of these characters catches a cold while travelling in the rain to meet her future husband. For ten points, name these characters who marry Mr. Bingley, Mr. Wickham, and Mr. Fitzwilliam Darcy in Jane Austen\u2019s Pride and Prejudice.", "answer": "the Bennet Sisters HALFTIME", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The accuracy of the coefficient of this chemical was questioned by Klenk, Komhyr and DeLuisi, who noticed significant inconsistencies in absorption data. A \u201ccyclic\u201d form of this molecule is likely to exist on the surface of magnesium oxide crystals in the air. A corona discharge tube can be used to generate this molecule, whose amount is measured in (*) Dobson units. The cleaving of alkenes and alkynes by this substance leads to rubber cracking. For 10 points, name this substance depleted by CFCs and present in its namesake \u201clayer\u201d in the stratosphere.", "answer": "ozone (accept O3)", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The name of this style originally referred to a style of painting known as Neue Sachlichkeit. One author who wrote in this style described the framing of General Canales for a murder committed by Zany the Beggar. Another author in this genre wrote about Carlos, Sophia and Esteban in the novel (*) Explosion in a Cathedral. One of the most famous writers in this genre wrote about the Clairvoyant Clara and Rosa the Beautiful, as well as other members of the Trueba family. For ten points name this literary genre used by Miguel Asturias, Alejo Carpentier, Isabel Allende, and Gabriel Garc\u00eda M\u00e1rquez, characterized by fantastical events in the real world.", "answer": "magical realism", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This man imprisoned the author Venko Markovski at his Goli Otok prison camp. Earlier in his career, this man liberated the short-lived Republic of U\u017eice. At the behest of Winston Churchill, this rival of Dra\u017ea Mihailovi\u0107 joined forces with Ivan \u0160uba\u0161i\u0107\u2019s government-in-exile. Though an early backer of the Cominform, this man split with (*) Joseph Stalin and the Soviet Union over this man\u2019s aggressively expansionist views. During World War II, this man and his Partisans became Europe\u2019s most effective anti-German resistance movement before forming a post-war socialist government. For ten points, name this notably independent longtime leader of Yugoslavia.", "answer": "Josip Tito", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Mahmoud keeps watch following the \u201cOcean Chorus\u201d in one of this man\u2019s operas, while another work by this man was commissioned by the Great Woods Festival and features a woodblock ostinato. A character in one of this man\u2019s operas is gifted a glass elephant after traveling on the Spirit of \u201876, and later watches the (*) Red Detachment of Women. A 1985 PLO hijacking inspired this man\u2019s The Death of Klinghoffer, and he was commissioned to write On the Transmigration of Souls following the September 11 attacks. For 10 points, name this modern American composer of Short Ride in a Fast Machine and Nixon in China.", "answer": "John Coolidge Adams", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The first day of this holiday marks the anniversary of medicine being given to mankind, while the last day sees men dine in the homes of their sisters. The death of Narakasura is celebrated in this holiday, which also involves the drawing of branched chalk designs called rangoli. This holiday begins a (*) new year for many merchants and business owners, and lamps called diyas are lit on this holiday to commemorate the return of Rama and Sita. For ten points, name this Hindu festival of lights which honors the goddess Lakshmi.", "answer": "Diwali (accept Divali, Dipvali, or Deepavali)", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "The Lin-Kernighan heuristic is one of the best strategies for solving this problem, and Christofides\u2019 algorithm solves this problem by constructing a minimum spanning tree. The \u201cbottleneck\u201d variety of this problem aims to minimize the weight of the weightiest edge in a cycle. This problem is equivalent to finding the (*) Hamiltonian cycle of lowest weight, and this NP-hard problem is a special case of the vehicle routing problem. For 10 points, name this problem which, given a list of cities and the distances between them, gives the shortest path that visits every city once and returns to the original city.", "answer": "travelling salesman problem (prompt on \u201cTSP\u201d)", "subcategory": "Science Computer Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one of this man\u2019s works, the Duke of Rothsay courts Catherine Glover but inadvertently angers Queen Mab. In another of this man\u2019s works, the priest Nourabad is distracted by a flaming village, allowing Leila to escape with her lover. Besides The Fair Maid of Perth, this man wrote an opera set on (*) Ceylon in which Nadir and Zurga sing \u201cAu fond du temple saint\u201d. Zuniga orders an arrest outside a cigarette factory in one of this man\u2019s works which sees Escamillo sing the \u201cToreador Song\u201d. For 10 points, name this French composer of operas like The Pearl Fishers and Carmen.", "answer": "Georges Bizet", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Audiovisual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A question posed to the main character of this novel asks \u201cDo you really live with the thought that when you die, you die, and nothing remains?\u201d The main character of this novel is enlisted to help his friend seduce and then spit into the face of his girlfriend after that friend, Raymond Sintes, suspects her of cheating. The protagonist of this novel shoots (*) an Arab five times after being threatened with a knife. In this novel, the protagonist doesn\u2019t cry at his mother\u2019s funeral, preferring to drink coffee and smoke instead. For ten points, name this novel about the indifferent French Algerian Meursault and written by Albert Camus.", "answer": "The Stranger (accept L\u2019\u00c9tranger or The Outsider)", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Followers of this philosophy are locked in flaming tombs in the Sixth Circle of Dante\u2019s Inferno. Evolving from the work of Aristippus of Cyrene, this school of philosophy was originally named \u201cthe Garden\u201d after the location of its first school. Lucretius advocated for this philosophy in his poem \u201cOn the Nature of Things\u201d and it was heavily influenced by the atomism of (*) Democritus. Followers of this philosophy seek ataraxia and aponia, or freedom from fear and the absence of bodily pain. For ten points, name this philosophy contrasted with Stoicism that holds that the only evil is suffering.", "answer": "Epicureanism", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "Frederick Lugard united the two halves of this country in 1914. One major conflict in this country followed the murder of Prime Minister Abubakar Tafawa Balewa and sparked the creation of Doctors without Borders. The \u201cCoup from Heaven\u201d in this country killed dictator Sani Abacha, who had executed activist Ken Siro-Wiwa for opposing (*) Royal Dutch Shell. This nation\u2019s first peaceful transition of elected power occurred after its 2015 elections, as Muhammadu Buhari defeated incumbent Goodluck Jonathan. For 10 points, name this most populous African country and home of Boko Haram whose largest city is Lagos.", "answer": "Nigeria", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One character with this occupation discusses another character\u2019s sleepwalking, and is surprised when that character sleepwalks towards him with a candle in hand. A character with this profession marries Heloise Dubuc, but marries another woman upon Heloise\u2019s death. Another character with this profession compares himself to Jesus in a poem titled \u201cHamlet.\u201d That character\u2019s (*) father kills himself by jumping in front of a train and loves a woman married to Pasha Antipov. Some famous authors who practiced this profession include W. Somerset Maugham, Arthur Conan Doyle, and Anton Chekhov. For ten points, name this profession practiced by those with an MD.", "answer": "doctor Bonuses", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "In the late 16th centuries, Russian tsars began to make their kingdom quite large. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Siberia", "Aleuts (or Aleutians)", "Elizabeth"], "parts": ["Russia\u2019s expansion was fueled by the conquest of this vast region, stretching from the Ural Mountains to the Pacific. Today, this region covers 77% of Russia\u2019s land area.", "During the conquest of Siberia, Russian authorities often perpetrated genocide on indigenous peoples, include this Northern Pacific ethnic group. A chain of northern Pacific islands are named for them.", "Many of the conquest\u2019s worst excesses occurred during the reign of this peaceful Russian empress. This daughter of Peter the Great gained power by deposing Ivan IV, who her niece-in-law Catherine the Great later executed."], "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "Famous practitioners of this sport include Joe Louis and Rocky Marciano. For ten points each:", "answers": ["boxing", "George Wesley Bellows", "New York City"], "parts": ["Name this violent sport depicted in Stag and Sharkey's which features athletes competing in a ring.", "Besides Stag and Sharkey\u2019s, this American artist portrayed boxers in his painting Dempsey and Firpo. This man created dozens of scenes of urban life in works like Men of the Docks.", "Bellow\u2019s Men of the Docks depicts a pier in this American city. Dempsey and Firpo is housed in this city\u2019s Whitney Museum of American Art."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "Types of these compounds are modelled as continuously flexible isotropic rods in the Kratky-Porod model. For ten points each:", "answers": ["polymers", "Ziegler\u2013Natta catalysts", "Teflon (accept PTFE or polytetrafluoroethylene)"], "parts": ["Name these general compounds that are chains of monomers.", "These compounds catalyze the polymerization of terminal alkenes. Heterogeneous types of these catalysts are based on titanium and are used with organoaluminum cocatalysts.", "This fluorine-containing polymer was discovered at DuPont. It is commonly used as a non-stick coating for pans because of its low coefficient of friction."], "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This man asked God to halt the Sun\u2019s movement in the sky in order to finish a battle against the Amorites. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Joshua", "Jericho", "twelve spies"], "parts": ["Name this Hebrew conqueror who succeeded Moses as leader of the Israelites.", "When besieging this city, Joshua ordered the Israelites to circle its walls for seven days. On the seventh day, the blowing of rams\u2019 horns caused the walls to crumble and enabled the Israelites to destroy this city.", "Earlier in his career, Joshua served in this group sent to explore the Promised Land. Of this group, only Joshua and Caleb reported back favorably."], "category": "Religion"}, {"leadin": "This movement began with the Declaration of Brijuni and promoted the <em>Panchsheel</em>, or five restraints. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Non-Aligned Movement (or NAM)", "Kwame Nkrumah", "Afghanistan"], "parts": ["Name this international political movement which rejected association with either communist or capitalist political blocs.", "The five founding fathers of the Non-Aligned Movement included this first president of Ghana. This strong advocate for Pan-Africanism was deposed in a US-backed coup in 1966.", "The Non-Aligned Movement suffered serious divisions after the Soviet Union\u2019s invasion of this nation in 1980. In response, the U.S. funded mujahedeen fighters in this nation, including future Taliban leaders."], "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This work opens with a woman writing physics equations on a board and another section in this work features characters chanting \u201cMr. Bojangles\u201d 58 times. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Einstein on the Beach", "Philip Glass", "film scores (or obvious equivalents)"], "parts": ["Name this minimalist composition with a run time of close to 5 hours that is broken up by 5 plotless \u201cknee plays\u201d.", "Einstein on the Beach is part of this American minimalist composer\u2019s Portrait Trilogy which also contains Satyagraha and Akhnaten.", "Glass is also famous for his work in this musical genre, including for Kundun, The Hours, and The Truman Show. John Williams has received 50 Oscar nominations for his work in this genre."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "This model replaced the predominant Davson\u2013Danielli model. For ten points each:", "answers": ["fluid mosaic model", "cell membrane (accept plasma membrane or cytoplasmic membrane)", "aquaporins"], "parts": ["Name this model proposed by Singer and Nicolson describing a bilayer of phospholipids.", "The fluid mosaic model applies to this selectively permeable cellular structure that surrounds the cytoplasm.", "These integral membrane proteins with NPA motifs serve as water channels through the cell membrane."], "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about colorfully titled novels. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Color Purple", "White Fang", "Jia Baoyu (accept either)"], "parts": ["This epistolary novel by Alice Walker about Celie\u2019s life in rural Georgia.", "The title dog of this Jack London novel abused by his first owner but is rescued by a California mining engineer.", "This character is the protagonist of Cao Xueqin\u2019s Dream of the Red Chamber. This man was born with a piece of the wall of heaven in his mouth, which took the form of jade."], "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "This civilization began to mass produce cylinder seals during its Uruk period. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Sumer (or Sumeria)", "ziggurats", "Ur"], "parts": ["Name this first great Mesopotamian civilization which pioneered large-scale agriculture and cuneiform.", "Sumerian cities constructed these massive temple complexes atop raised platforms. These structures were possibly built to house various gods.", "The Great Ziggurat was built near this Sumerian city on the mouth of the Euphrates River. This city is commonly suggested to be the birthplace of Abraham."], "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This thinker believed his subjects used \u201cschemata\u201d to learn about the outside world and could either assimilate or accommodate new information. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Jean Piaget", "induction", "conservation"], "parts": ["Name this Swiss psychologist who theorized about four stages of child development.", "According to Piaget, this type of reasoning marks the preoperational stage stage of development. In science, this skill is used to derive general understanding from specific observations.", "Piaget believed that this concept indicate the concrete operational stage of child development. Piaget tested this skill through pouring water in differently sized glasses."], "category": "Social Science"}, {"leadin": "These sets have non-integer Hausdorff dimensions. For ten points each:", "answers": ["fractals", "Peano curves", "arithmetic"], "parts": ["Name these self-similar objects that include the Menger sponge and Sierpinski\u2019s triangle.", "These space-filling fractal curves have a Hausdorff dimension of 2. A variant of these curves is named for David Hilbert.", "Giuseppe Peano\u2019s namesake axioms formalized this branch of mathematics. This field\u2019s fundamental theorem is the unique factorization theorem."], "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This economic program includes the \u201cThree Arrows\u201d of monetary easing, fiscal stimulus, and structural reform. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Abenomics", "Japan", "Liberal Democratic Party (accept LDP or Jimint\u014d or Liberal Democrats)"], "parts": ["Name this set of policies designed to revive a long-stagnating East Asian economy.", "Abenomics take their name from Shinz\u014d Abe, the prime minister of this nation. This country\u2019s pacifist constitution was primarily drafted by the United States following World War Two.", "In Japan\u2019s October 2017, this conservative party led by Abe won a supermajority of seats. A similarly named party in the United Kingdom was once led by Nick Clegg."], "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This scientist introduced the idea that a gene is an aperiodic crystal. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Erwin Rudolf Josef Alexander Schr\u00f6dinger", "dead and alive", "Copenhagen interpretation"], "parts": ["Name this physicist who wrote What Is Life? and whose namesake equation can be solved by the Hartree\u2013Fock method.", "Schr\u00f6dinger proposed a thought experiment presenting a cat in two states simultaneously. Name both states.", "In his thought experiment, Schr\u00f6dinger\u2019s sought to illustrate the absurdity of this interpretation of quantum mechanics, which states that physical systems do not possess definite properties before being measured."], "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "In this novel, one character partially learns of speech and humanity by reading <em>The Sorrows of Young Werther</em> and <em>Plutarch\u2019s Lives</em>. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Frankenstein", "Elizabeth Lavenza (accept either)", "epistolary"], "parts": ["Name this Mary Shelley novel about a doctor who reanimates a monster. This novel is subtitled \u201cThe Modern Prometheus.\u201d", "Frankenstein\u2019s monster murders this person, Frankenstein\u2019s fianc\u00e9e, on their wedding night because Frankenstein refused to make the monster a mate.", "This word can describe the form of Frankenstein because much of the novel is told in a series of letters from Robert Walton."], "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "This group included a son of Poseidon and Gaia who was invincible as long as he was touching the ground. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Titans", "Mnemosyne", "Atlas"], "parts": ["Name this group from Greek mythology, led by Cronus and Rhea, which was overthrown by Zeus and preceded the Olympians.", "This titaness of memory was worshipped in the cult of Asclepius, the god of medicine, and was the mother of the nine Muses.", "This titan was the father of the Hesperides and the Pleiades and was forced to hold the Earth on his shoulders for all eternity. This being names a mountain range in Morocco."], "category": "Mythology"}, {"leadin": "In this battle, Joseph Hooker\u2019s First Corps suffered heavy losses in Miller\u2019s Cornfield. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Battle of Antietam (or Battle of Sharpsburg)", "George B. McClellan", "cigars"], "parts": ["Name this devastating 1862 battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single day battle in U.S. history. President Lincoln used this mild Union victory to announce the Emancipation Proclamation.", "This man led Union forces at the Battle of Antietam. Known both for his crippling indecision and popularity with the army, this general later challenged Lincoln for the presidency in 1864.", "McClellan was aided at Antietam by the discovery of Confederate Special Order 191 wrapped around three of these items. Union General William T. Sherman was a consummate consumer of these items."], "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "In one scene in this novel, the protagonist believes his brains are melting when he puts on a helmet filled with cheese curds. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Don Quixote", "windmills", "Amadis of Gaul"], "parts": ["Name this novel by Miguel de Cervantes about the adventures of a delusional \u201cknight,\u201d his horse Rocinante, and his squire Sancho Panza.", "Don Quixote accidentally tries to fight these things during one of his adventures, which he mistakenly believes to be giants.", "Many of Don Quixote\u2019s delusions come from stories of this knight \u201cof Gaul.\u201d"], "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about cities named Columbia. For ten points each:", "answers": ["South Carolina", "I-95", "University of Missouri (or Mizzou)"], "parts": ["Columbia is the capital of this southern Palmetto state where Charleston is the largest city.", "Columbia, Maryland is located just off of this major East Coast interstate running from Miami to Maine. It replaced US-1 as the region\u2019s primary north-south highway in the early 1970s.", "Another city named Columbia contains this large state university, home to the world\u2019s oldest journalism school and whose mascot is Truman the Tiger."], "category": "Geography"}, {"leadin": "In this novel, Amir and his father leave their country to Peshawar, then the United States, where Amir\u2019s father works as a gas station manager. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Kite Runner", "Kabul", "Hazara"], "parts": ["Name this Khaled Hosseini novel titled after a competition which involves slicing the strings of flying toys.", "The Kite Runner takes place in this capital city of Afghanistan where Amir spends his childhood.", "Amir\u2019s best friend, Hassan, is part of this ethnic group, which is persecuted relentlessly when the Taliban comes to power."], "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Poetry and composers seems to go well together. For ten points each:", "answers": ["\u201cOde to Joy\u201d", "The Lark Ascending", "Aaron Copland"], "parts": ["Name this poem by Friedrich Schiller, set to music in 1824 by Ludwig van Beethoven in his Symphony No. 9.", "A solo violin mimics the actions of the title bird in this George Meredith poem set to music by the composer of Fantasia on a Theme by Thomas Tallis, and Fantasia on Greensleeves.", "This composer set many poems to music, including text by E.E. Cummings, and twelve poems by Emily Dickinson."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "This man was wounded while helping his father capture the city of Ceuta. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Henry the Navigator", "Prester John", "Vasco da Gama"], "parts": ["Name this Portuguese prince whose interest and funding helped spark the Age of Exploration.", "Henry\u2019s fascination with exploration was in part fueled by the legend of this man, who supposedly ruled a vast Christian kingdom in the east. Later Europeans assigned this man\u2019s identity to the Emperor of Ethiopia.", "Though Portuguese voyages never left the Gulf of Guinea in Henry\u2019s lifetime, this Portuguese captain sailed as far as India in 1498, becoming the first European to do so."], "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}]}